James Simmons papers, 1945-1996
Emory University
- Writings by others, Series 5; Boxes 65-70
  - Poetry by others, Subseries 5.1; Box 65-Box 69
    - O'Kelly, Jon, "Ponderessur," MS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - O'Kelly, Jon, "Romance," MS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - O'Kelly, Jon, "A Worthy Troubadour," MS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - O'Toole, Bridget, "Punctuation," TS (Box 68, Folder 11)
    - Oyeyipo, T.A., Yoruba Song, TS (Box 68, Folder 12)
    - Patterson Jessie, "Why Don't I Mean What You Say?," TS (Box 68, Folder 13)
    - Quin, Deirdre, Poems Submitted for Creative Work, MS (Box OP)
    - Quin, Deirdre, Where the Cap Fits Wear It!, MS (Box 68, Folder 14)
    - Rice, Adrian, "Bread of Sorrows," TS (Box 68, Folder 15)
    - Rice, Adrian, "The Little Pig," TS (Box 68, Folder 16)
    - Rice, Adrian, "The Mason's Tongue," TS (Box 68, Folder 17)
    - Rice, Adrian, "Serpents in the Heart," TS (Box 68, Folder 18)
    - Ritsos, Yannis, Corridor and Stairs, TS (Box 68, Folder 19)
    - Robertson, Denise, "Pit Closure," TS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - Rodgers, Bill and Derek Simpson, Kingdom Come, TS (Box 68, Folder 20)
    - Santos, Sherod, "Belfast Arioso," TS (Box 68, Folder 21)
    - Shepherd, Graham S., "'Omnibus' on James Simmons," TS (Box 68, Folder 22)
    - Shepherd, Graham S., "Two Old Whores," TS (Box 68, Folder 23)
    - Simmons, Anna, "Graveyard," MS (Box 68, Folder 24)
    - Simmons, Anna, "Happy Christmas," MS (Box 68, Folder 25)
    - Simmons, Anna, "Midnight Valley," TS (Box 68, Folder 26)
    - Simmons, Rachel, "Snow," MS [See Subseries 5.1, Poetry by Others, Simmons, Anna, "Happy Christmas"]
    - Simmons, Rachel, "Song," TSS (Box 68, Folder 27)
    - Smith, Stevie, "A Soldier Dear to Us," TSS [See also Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman] (Box 68, Folder 28)
    - Soyinka, Wole, "My Next Door Neighbour," TS (Box 68, Folder 29)
    - Squires, Jon, "Aisling," MS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - Squires, Jon, "The Campaign," MS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - Squires, Jon, "My Friend," MS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - Squires, Jon, "West-North-West," MS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - Stephens, Michael, "The Artist on His Way to Work," TS (Box 68, Folder 30)
    - Stephens, Michael, "Blues for Chocolate Doherty," TS (Box 68, Folder 31)
    - Stephens, Michael, "Breaking Up With Harry," TS (Box 68, Folder 32)
    - Stephens, Michael, "The Butterfly's Lesson to Buster Keaton," TS [See Subseries 5.1, Poetry by Others, Stephens Michael, "The Artist on His Way to Work"]
    - Stephens, Michael, "Castaway," TS (Box 68, Folder 33)
    - Stephens, Michael, "Death of a Lonely Private," TS (Box 68, Folder 34)
    - Stephens, Michael, "Don't Wanna Come Down," TS (Box 68, Folder 35)
    - Stephens, Michael, "The Dream King,," TS (Box 68, Folder 36)
    - Stephens, Michael, "Energy to Burn," TS (Box 68, Folder 37)
    - Stephens, Michael, "Even Cowgirls Get the Blues," TS (Box 68, Folder 38)
    - Stephens, Michael, "Greatest Game of Tennis," TS (Box 68, Folder 39)
    - Stephens, Michael, "I Think It Was Michael Stephens Who Said...," TS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - Stephens, Michael, "The Importance of Free Thought, TS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - Stephens, Michael, "My Nobody Neurosis," TS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - Stephens, Michael, "My Ship," TS (Box 68, Folder 40)
    - Stephens, Michael, "No for an Answer," TS (Box 68, Folder 41)
    - Stephens, Michael, "One Last Chance," TS (Box 68, Folder 42)
    - Stephens, Michael, "The Pleasure Drome," TS (Box 68, Folder 43)
    - Stephens, Michael, "Prose Peace," TS (Box 68, Folder 44)
    - Stephens, Michael, "Schooldays," TS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - Stephens, Michael, "Shakespeare," TS [See Subseries 5.1, Poetry by Others, Stephens, Michael, "Prose Peace"]
    - Stephens, Michael, "To the Daughter of the Presbyterian Minister," TS (Box 68, Folder 45)
    - Stephens, Michael, "Toscanini," TS [See Subseries 5.1, Poetry by Others, Stephens, Michael, "Prose Peace"]
    - Stephens, Michael, "A Walk in the Sea," TS (Box 68, Folder 46)
    - Stephens, Michael, "What It Is," TS (Box 68, Folder 47)
    - Stephens, Michael, "What the Woman Next Door Was," TS (Box 68, Folder 48)
    - Stephens, Michael, "Will It Stand Up in Public?," TS (Box 68, Folder 49)
    - Stinson, Laura, "The Club Piper," MS (Box 68, Folder 50)
    - Stinson, Laura, "Memory Lane," MS (Box 68, Folder 51)
    - Strain, Anne, "Drums," TS (Box 68, Folder 52)
    - Strain, Anne, "Renascence," TS (Box 68, Folder 53)
    - Strain, Anne, "Seasons," TS (Box 68, Folder 54)
    - Strain, Anne, "Spleen," TS (Box 68, Folder 55)
    - Strain, Anne, "Window-Dressing," TS (Box 68, Folder 56)
    - Sylvestre, Anne, "La Rochelle," TSS (Box 68, Folder 57)
    - Templeton, David M., "Earth to Earth, Ashes to Electrons," TS (Box 68, Folder 58)
    - Turner, W. Price, "Full Supporting Programme," TS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - Turner, W. Price, "The Moral Rocking-Horse," TS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - Turner, W. Price, "A Northern Tragedy," TS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - Turner, W. Price, "Procrastination," TS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - Turner, W. Price, "Prop and Prodder," TS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - Turner, W. Price, "The Queer Spleen Face," TS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - Turner, W. Price, "Rose Harem," TS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - Waddams, Keith, "After Colchis," TS (Box 68, Folder 59)
    - Waddams, Keith, "Bip Goes to a Formal Party," TS (Box 68, Folder 60)
    - Waddams, Keith, "Political Poems," TS (Box 68, Folder 61)
    - Waddams, Keith, "Willie and Hell," TS (Box 68, Folder 62)
    - Watson, Arthur, "James Simmons," TS (Box 69, Folder 1)
    - Weir, Anthony, from Tide and Undertow, TS (Box 69, Folder 2)
    - Weiskopf, James, "Five Songs Without Words," MS (Box 69, Folder 3)
    - Wichert, Sabine, "Competing for Lesser Evils," TS (Box 69, Folder 4)
    - Wichert, Sabine, "On Liberty," TS (Box 69, Folder 5)
    - Wright, Maxwell, "On Reading Stephen Spender," TS [See also Subseries 3.1, Uncollected Poetry, "The Unhappy Warrior"] (Box 69, Folder 6)
    - Wright, Maxwell, "Sonnet on Sonnets," TS (Box 69, Folder 7)
    - Wright, Maxwell, "Sonnet 3," TS [See Subseries 5.1, Poetry by Others, Wright Maxwell, "Sonnet on Sonnets"]
    - Young, Augustus, "Ballad of the Aberdeen Oilman," TS (Box 69, Folder 8)
    - Young, Augustus, "The Humours of Bandon," TS (Box 69, Folder 9)
    - Zell, Ann, "Beachfind," TSS (Box 69, Folder 10)
    - Zell, Ann, "Dysfunction," TSS (Box 69, Folder 11)
    - Zell, Ann, "First Visit," TSS (Box 69, Folder 12)
    - Zell, Ann, "Gainfully Unemployed," TSS (Box 69, Folder 13)
    - Zell, Ann, "Nature Programme," TSS (Box 69, Folder 14)
    - Zell, Ann, "Partial Eclipse," TSS (Box 69, Folder 15)
    - Zell, Ann, "Storm Morning," TSS (Box 69, Folder 16)
    - Zell, Ann, "Walking Home Alone, Drunk," TSS (Box 69, Folder 17)
    - Zell, Ann, "Water Rites," TSS (Box 69, Folder 18)
    - Zell, Ann, "The Woman Who Wanted to be Wild," TSS (Box 69, Folder 19)
    - By title (author unknown)
    - "Accounts," TS (Box 69, Folder 20)
    - "Bastille Day," TS (Box 69, Folder 21)
    - "Before Leaving Europe," MS (Box 69, Folder 22)
    - "The Beggar Woman," TS (Box 69, Folder 23)
    - "Belfast," MS (Box 69, Folder 24)
    - "Blanche Dubois," MS (Box 69, Folder 25)
    - "Caliban," TS (Box 69, Folder 26)
    - "The Celtic Clairvoyant," TS (Box 69, Folder 27)
    - "Child After the Rain," TS [See Subseries 5.1, Poetry by Others, "The Beggar Woman"]
    - "Children Drinking," MS (Box 69, Folder 28)
    - "Could I Have Spoken?" TS (Box 69, Folder 29)
    - "Curse," MS (Box 69, Folder 30)
    - "Daily Bread," TS (Box 69, Folder 31)
    - "Death of a Painter," MS (Box 69, Folder 32)
    - "Departure," TS (Box 69, Folder 33)
    - "Esk," MS (Box 69, Folder 34)
    - "Estampie," TS (Box 69, Folder 35)
    - "Farewell...Farewell," TS (Box 69, Folder 36)
    - "Ferry Aid," MS (Box 69, Folder 37)
    - "Flame Child," MS (Box 69, Folder 38)
    - "The Freedom of Wolves," TS (Box 69, Folder 39)
    - "From the Bottom of My Heart," TS (Box 69, Folder 40)
    - "Haikus for the Fitzpatrick," MS (Box 69, Folder 41)
    - "Herring Run," TS (Box 69, Folder 42)
    - "Homing," TS (Box 69, Folder 43)
    - "I Dream You Loose America," TS (Box 69, Folder 44)
    - "In Confidence," TS (Box 69, Folder 45)
    - "John Stone Seen Playing at Evening," TS [See Subseries 5.1, Poetry by Others, "The Beggar Woman"]
    - "A Landscape for Edward Thomas," TS (Box 69, Folder 46)
    - "Letters Home," TS (Box 69, Folder 47)
    - "Lightning Struck my Dad's Chrysler," TS (Box 69, Folder 48)
    - "Lines," TS (Box 69, Folder 49)
    - "Lyric for a 'Pop,'" TS (Box 69, Folder 50)
    - "Mango Breasts," TS [See Subseries 5.1, Poetry by Others, "The Beggar Woman"]
    - "The Masterpiece," MS (Box 69, Folder 51)
    - "The Midnight Invasion at Mousetown," TS (Box 69, Folder 52)
    - "Moon Song," MS (Box 69, Folder 53)
    - "Music Night in the Windsor Castle," MS (Box 69, Folder 54)
    - "Navtivity," MS (Box 69, Folder 55)
    - "Oedipus Put Out His Eyes," TS [See Subseries 5.1, Poetry by Others, "Could I Have Spoken?"]
    - "Poisonous Hours," MS (Box 69, Folder 56)
    - "Questions to an Irish Poet...For James Simmons," TS (Box 69, Folder 57)
    - "The Resusciation of Arthur's Fair Lady," TS (Box 69, Folder 58)
    - "Routine," TS (Box 69, Folder 59)
    - "Saint Valentine's Day," TS (Box 69, Folder 60)
    - "Slemish," TS (Box 69, Folder 61)
    - "The Songs of the P.W.D. Man," TS (Box 69, Folder 62)
    - "Spiral Dance," TS [See Subseries 5.1, Poetry by Others, "The Beggar Woman"]
    - "Sunday Morning Stroll," TS (Box 69, Folder 63)
    - "Telephone Conversation," TS [See Subseries 5.1, Poetry by Others, "Routine"]
    - "Thrush," TS (Box 69, Folder 64)
    - "To a Young Lady in the Prospect of Suicide," TS (Box 69, Folder 65)
    - "To a Porpoise," TS [See Subseries 5.1, Poetry by Others, "The Beggar Woman"]
    - "To Two Good Poents Men," MS (Box 69, Folder 66)
    - "Two Travellers," MS (Box 69, Folder 67)
    - "Unclaimed Wilderness," MS (Box 69, Folder 68)
    - "Variables, " TS [See Subseries 5.1, Poetry by Others, "The Beggar Woman"]
    - "A Visit," TS (Box 69, Folder 69)
    - "A West Strand Vision: for Jimmy," TS (Box 69, Folder 70)
    - "Wound," TS (Box 69, Folder 71)
    - Untitled (Box 69, Folder 72)
  - Prose by others, Subseries 5.2; Box 70
    - Writings about Simmons
    - Durcan, Paul, Review of Simmons' music, TS (Box 70, Folder 1)
    - Johnstone, Robert, " Sex, Rectitude, and Loneliness," TS (Box 70, Folder 2)
    - Kavanagh, P.J., "Honest in Ulster," TS (Box 70, Folder 3)
    - McGlone, Glen, "from Sex, Rectiude, and Loneliness," MS (Box 70, Folder 4)
    - Sexton, Brian, Review of Constantly Singing, TS (Box 70, Folder 5)
    - Stinson, Peter, Review of James Simmons's From the Irish, TS (Box 70, Folder 6)
    - " The Rostrevor Sessions," MS (Box 70, Folder 7)
    - " Sex, Rectitude, and Loneliness," MS (Box 70, Folder 8)
    - "Talking to James Simmons," TS (Box 70, Folder 9)
    - Other Prose
    - Bell, Sam Hanna, "Country Bard," Radio Script (Box 70, Folder 10)
    - Christensen, Soren, "King Lindworm," TS [Translated by Sarah Simmons] (Box 70, Folder 11)
    - Cooke, Emma, "How to Write Haiku," TS (Box 70, Folder 12)
    - Fay, Don, "Walking Over Graves," TSS (Box 70, Folder 13)
    - Foley, Michael, "The Movies," TS (Box 70, Folder 14)
    - Genet, Jacqueline, "The Dialectic of Nature and Spirit in W.B. Yeats' Poetry," TS (Box 70, Folder 15)
    - Glancy, N.N., "Irish Medical Lore," TS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - Hearsum, John, "The Running of Things," TS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - Hewitt, John, "Alec of the Chimney Corner," TS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Editedby Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - Ibarra, Eileen S., "Thomas Davis and Irish Literature," TS (Box 70, Folder 16)
    - Kazmi, S.N.R., "W.B. Yeats and the Rhymers' Club," TS (Box 70, Folder 17)
    - MacColl, Ewan, and Charles Parker, "The Big Hewer," Radio Script (Box 70, Folder 18)
    - Martin, Penelope, "Much Hatred Little Sense," TS (Box 70, Folder 19)
    - McBreen, Joan, "Introducing Eavan Boland, Poet," TS (Box 70, Folder 20)
    - McBreen, Joan, "Major Changes in the Lives of Women in Ireland 1940-1990, TS (Box 70, Folder 21)
    - Meir, Colin, "Yeats and the Translations from the Gaelic," TS (Box 70, Folder 22)
    - Montgomery, Derek, "Letter From America," TS [See also Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman] (Box 70, Folder 23)
    - Morrow, John, "Bazaar," TS (Box 70, Folder 24)
    - O'Kelly, Jon, "A Talent Lost is a Tear in Heaven," MS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - O'Malley, Mary, "Irish Theatre Letter," TS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - O'Toole, Bridget, Review of Brenda Maddox's Nora: A Biography of Nora Joyce, TS (Box 70, Folder 25)
    - Parker, Charles, "Landmarks," Radio Script (Box 70, Folder 26)
    - Stephens, Michael, "Drugs V. Drink," TS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - Stephens, Michael, "Interview with Roger McGough," TS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - Stephens, Michael, "The Sky At Night," TS (Box 70, Folder 27)
    - Stewart, Alexander, "I Thought I Heard a Shot," MS (Box 70, Folder 28)
    - Stewart, John D., "Let Us Be Human," TS [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - Taylor, Mary, "Ants," TS (Box 70, Folder 29)
    - Taylor, Mary, "Special Gifts," TS (Box 70, Folder 30)
    - Young, Augustus, "Cork 1964," TS (Box 70, Folder 31)
    - "James' Little Girl," MS (Box 70, Folder 32)
    - "The Old WPA Swimming Pool at Martin's Ferry, Ohio," TS (Box 70, Folder 33)
    - "Poems from the North," Radio Script (Box 70, Folder 34)
    - "South of Boston," TS (Box 70, Folder 35)
    - Untitled Novel, TS (Box 70, Folder 36)
    - Untitled (Box 70, Folder 37)
- Printed material, Series 6; Boxes 71-77, OP 11-20
  The James Simmons papers include many collected publications-clippings and entire magazines and journals-with material by or about Simmons. These printed materials have been arranged alphabetically by type: writings by Simmons, writings about Simmons, and other collected printed material.
  Organized into three subseries: (6.1) Writings by Simmons, (6.2) Writings about Simmons, and (6.3) Other printed material.
  - Writings by Simmons, Subseries 6.1; Box 71
    - Publications with poems and songs
    - "An American Settler's Soliloquy" (Box 71, Folder 1)
    - "Another Poet" [See Subseries 3.5, Notebooks, Box 47, Folder 1]
    - "Art and Reality," in the Irish Press, 29 August 1965 [See Subseries 3.5, Notebooks, Box 47, Folder 1]
    - "The Baggage and the Toff," in The Irish Press, 29 April 1978 (Box 71, Folder 2)
    - "The Ballad of Donnell and Eileen" (Box 71, Folder 3)
    - "The Ballad of Gerry Kelly the Newsagent," in Belfast Telegraph, 2 March 1973 (Box 71, Folder 4)
    - "Ballad of a Marriage" (Box 71, Folder 5)
    - "The Ballad of Ranger Best" [See Subseries 6.1, Printed Material, Writings by Simmons, "The Ballad of Gerry Kelly the Newsagent"]
    - "The Bonfire," in The Honest Ulsterman, December 1969 (Box 71, Folder 6)
    - "Brown's Bay, Sunday, October," in Stet, Winter 1993 (Box 71, Folder 7)
    - "The Catholic Church's Reveng on James Joyce," in The Poetry Book Society Bulletin (Box 71, Folder 8)
    - "Censorship" (Box 71, Folder 9)
    - "A Child Asks Why" [See Subseries 3.5, Notebooks, Box 47, Folder 1]
    - "Claudy" [See Subseries 6.1, Printed Material, Writings by Simmons, "The Ballad of Gerry Kelly the Newsagent"]
    - "Cloncha," in The Irish Press, 26 August 1978 (Box 71, Folder 10)
    - "Confession" [See Subseries 6.1, Printed Material, Writings by Simmons, "An American Settler's Soliloquy"]
    - "Declaration of Dependence" (Box 71, Folder 11)
    - "Deirdre-A Fragment" (Box 71, Folder 12)
    - "D.H. Lawrence," in Fortnight, 2 April 1976 (Box 71, Folder 13)
    - "Elegy for a Deadborn Child" (Box 71, Folder 14)
    - "Eng. Soc. Sec." (Box 71, Folder 15)
    - "For Delphine" (Box 71, Folder 16)
    - "Frankie and Johnny Got Married" (Box 71, Folder 17)
    - "The Harvest is Past?" (Box 71, Folder 18)
    - "The Heart of the Matter," in Fortnight, 2 April 1976 [See Subseries 6.1, Printed Material, Writings by Simmons, "D.H. Lawrence"]
    - "I Hated Africans," in Listener, 15 January 1970 (Box 71, Folder 19)
    - "I Like it Here" [See also Subseries 3.5, Notebooks, Box 47, Folder 1] (Box 71, Folder 20)
    - "The Interned Bomber" [See Subseries 6.1, Printed Material, Writings by Simmons, "The Ballad of Gerry Kelly the Newsagent"]
    - "Johnny My Gigolo" (Box 71, Folder 21)
    - "Kill the Children" [See Subseries 6.1, Printed Material, Writings by Simmons, "The Ballad of Gerry Kelly the Newsagent"]
    - "Lullaby for Rachel," in the Belfast Telegraph, 9 March 1963 (Box 71, Folder 22)
    - "Man is a Soldier," in The Times Literary Supplement, 13 October 1961 (Box 71, Folder 23)
    - "The Maze" (Box 71, Folder 24)
    - "from Memorials of a Tour in Yorkshire" (Box 71, Folder 25)
    - "Nigeria 1967," in The Honest Ulsterman, December 1969 [See Subseries 6.1, Printed Material, Writings by Simmons, "The Bonfire"]
    - "The Not Yet Ancient Mariner" (Box 71, Folder 26)
    - "Ode to My Grandmother" [See also Subseries 3.5, Notebooks, Box 47, Folder 1] (Box 71, Folder 27)
    - "Olive and Davy," in The Irish Press, 24 November 1979 (Box 71, Folder 28)
    - "Outward Bound," in the Irish Press, 29 August 1968 [See Suberies 3.5, Notebooks, Box 47, Folder 1]
    - "Peasant Quality" (Box 71, Folder 29)
    - "Protestant Courts Catholic" [See Subseries, 3.5, Notebooks, Box 47, Folder 1]
    - "The Refugee's Song" (Box 71, Folder 30)
    - "Roots" [See Subseries 3.5, Notebooks, Box 47, Folder 1]
    - The Rostrevor Sessions (Box 71, Folder 31)
    - "from Sex, Rectitude, and Loneliness" (Box 71, Folder 32)
    - Sex, Rectitude, and Loneliness (Box 71, Folder 33)
    - "Stephano Remembers," in The Irish Times, 3 May 1969 [See Subseries 3.5, Notebooks, Box 47, Folder 1]
    - "That Sailor" [See Subseries 6.1, Printed Material, Writings by Simmons, "An American Settler's Soliloquy"]
    - "Ulster Fragments" [See Subseries 6.1, Printed Material, Writings by Simmons, "The Ballad of Gerry Kelly the Newsagent"]
    - "Von Stroheim," in Fortnight, 2 April 1976 [See Subseries 6.1, Printed Material, Writings by Simmons, "D.H. Lawrence"]
    - "War Record" [See also Subseries 3.5, Notebooks, Box 47, Folder 1] (Box 71, Folder 34)
    - "The Weather" [See Subseries 3.5, Notebooks, Box 47, Folder 1]
    - "What Will You Do, Love?" (Box 71, Folder 35)
    - "Woman in the Harbour" (Box 71, Folder 36)
    - Publications with prose
    - "Author of Poem Replies to 'Pornographic' Charge" [see Subseries 3.5, Notebooks, Box 47, Folder 1]
    - "Channel Crossing" in The Gryphon, January 1956 (Box 71, Folder 37)
    - "Christianity and Contemporary Literature," in Crunch!, 20 June 1968 (Box 71, Folder 38)
    - "Christianity's Worst Enemies Are in the Various Churches" (Box 71, Folder 39)
    - Comments on The Selected James Simmons in The Poetry Book Society Bulletin, Summer 1978 (Box 71, Folder 40)
    - Comments on Constantly Singing in The Poetry Book Society Bulletin, Summer 1980 (Box 71, Folder 41)
    - "Derry Boy," in Fortnight, 30 April, 1971 [review of James Carrick's With O'Leary to the Grave] (Box 71, Folder 42)
    - "Dr. Conrad" (Box 71, Folder 43)
    - "The Drunken Writer," in Hibernia, July 1969 [See Subseries 3.5, Notebooks, Box 47, Folder 1]
    - "Ex-Moderator's Views on Censorship 'Silly and Dangerous'" [See also Subseries 3.5, Notebooks, Box 47, Folder 1] (Box 71, Folder 44)
    - "A Gathering of Eagles" (Box 71, Folder 45)
    - The Honest Ulsterman, May, 1968 [See Subseries 3.6, Works Edited by Simmons, The Honest Ulsterman]
    - The Honest Ulsterman Tables of Contents (Box 71, Folder 46)
    - "The Humour of Deprivation," in Irish Writers and the Theatre (Box 71, Folder 47)
    - "James Simmons" (Box 71, Folder 48)
    - "James Simmons--Introduction" (Box 71, Folder 49)
    - "James Simmons: Life and Work" (Box 71, Folder 50)
    - "Juno and the Paycock," Chapter in Simmons's Sean O'Casey (Box 71, Folder 51)
    - "Laying Down Laws for Love (Box 71, Folder 52)
    - "Michael Longley," in Fortnight, 4 December 1970 (Box 71, Folder 53)
    - "More Notes Towards a Revolution: Overheard in a Bar in the City," in The Honest Ulsterman, 15 July 1969 (Box 71, Folder 54)
    - "Mr. Nicholas" (Box 71, Folder 55)
    - "My First Love" (Box 71, Folder 56)
    - "National Geographic Poetry" [review of Tony Harrison's The Loiners] (Box 71, Folder 57)
    - "New Talent," in Fortnight, 22 June 1973 [reveiw of Michael Hartnett's Selected Poems] (Box 71, Folder 58)
    - "The Old School Tie," in The Education Times, 28 June 1973 (Box 71, Folder 59)
    - Review of Patrick Boyle's All Looks Yellow to the Jaundiced Eye (Box 71, Folder 60)
    - Review of Patrick Kavanagh's Almost Everything [See Subseries 6.1, Printed Material, Writings by Simmons, Review of Patrick Boyle's All Looks Yellow to the Jaundiced Eye]
    - Review of John Hewitt's The Day of the Corncrake (Box 71, Folder 61)
    - Review of Thomas Kilroy's The Death and Resurrection of Mr. Roche (Box 71, Folder 62)
    - Review of Gavin Ewart's The Deceptive Grin of the Gravel Porters (Box 71, Folder 63)
    - Review of Seamus Heaney's Door Into the Dark (Box 71, Folder 64)
    - Review of James L. McAuley's Draft Balance Sheet [See Subseries 6.1, Printed Material, Writings by Simmons, Review of Thomas Kilroy's The Death and Resurrection of Mr. Roche]
    - Review of Brian Moore's Fergus (Box 71, Folder 65)
    - Review of the Lyric Theatre's production of The Heart's a Wonder," in Fortnight, 5 February 1971 (Box 71, Folder 66)
    - Review of Brian Moore's I Am Mary Dunne (Box 71, Folder 67)
    - Review of Murder in the Cathedral, in Sage, Summer 1970 (Box 71, Folder 68)
    - Review of John Montague and Seamus Heaney's The Northern Muse (Box 71, Folder 69)
    - Review of Che Guevara's Reminscences of the Cuban Revolutionary War (Box 71, Folder 70)
    - Review of John Montague's Tides (Box 71, Folder 71)
    - "Riots and Writing," in Hibernia, 10 October 1969 [see Subseries 3.5, Notebooks, Box 47, Folder 1]
    - "The Smoke of Their Torment Ascendeth," in The Spectator, 30 April 1994 [review of Edna O'Brien's House of Splendid Isolation] (Box 71, Folder 72)
    - "Staying in Print," in The Poetry Book Society Bulletin [See Subseries 6.1, Printed Material, Writings by Simmons, "The Catholic Church's Revenge on James Joyce"]
    - "Ulster's Heart," [review of Sam Hanna Bell's December Bride (Box 71, Folder 73)